#### FESTUS K. MUTAITI

# P.O. BOX 101603 - 00101, Nairobi, Kenya

**Mobile:** +254723 641 879/0736595556 *E-mail:* mutaitifestus@gmail.com

Gender: Male, Nationality: Kenyan, Date of Birth: Sep 27, 1984, ID No. 23496386, PIN No.

A004131006M

Languages spoken: English, Swahili Marital status: Married

#### **CAREER OBJECTIVE**

I seek challenging and rewarding career opportunity within a dynamic and progressive organization that will utilize my knowledge and acquired skills and work experience while encouraging and supporting professional, community, organizational growth and perfect myself through continuous improvement and self-development but deliver to the best through teamwork.

#### PERSONAL PROLILE

Self-driven and motivated, honest, hardworking, flexible, goal oriented and able to work under pressure, with high interpersonal, planning, analytical and organizational skills; a result-oriented individual with strong technical skills and great aptitude to learn

## **EDUCATION BACKGROUND**

2007 – 2011: B. Sc. in Food Science & Technology, Second class – Upper Division

Egerton University, Njoro Campus

**2005-2005:** Kenya Certificate of secondary Education Mean Grade B+ (Plus)

Mumbuni High School- Machakos

#### HONOURS AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- > Actively represented Bio Food Products Ltd in the KEBS Dairy Technical Comittee since 2019
- As Bio Production Manager, I managed to reduce the production wastages from over 5% to below 0.5%; Reduced overtimes by 15% and stretching of straff by improving work/people organization and effectiveness in machine utilization.
- Awarded a Gold award of the president's Award Kenya by His Excellency President Hon. Mwai kibaki at state house (August 2008); also a Silver and Bronze Awards holder
- As the head of the Quality Assurance team at Bio Food Products Ltd, I successfully spearheaded the designing quality standards and the production monitoring procedures there by maintaining delivery of high quality Yoghurts used by british airways, Kenya airways cooperate markets and as well as implementation of internal staff Trainings
- As the Quality Assurance Manager at Meru Dairy Cooperative Union, I was recognized with a package of a fully paid trip for two week training at Dudhmotisagar Dairy in Haryana, India for exemplary performance and competence in establishing and maintaining company's quality standards

#### PROFESSIONAL WORK EXPERIENCE

## **BIO FOOD PRODUCTS LIMITED**

From: Feb 2019 to August 2021: Position: Production Manager

**Role:** 

Reporting to the Manufacturing director; mandated to overseeing the overall production operations on yoghurt, Long life products, and the Fine Food Company products.

#### **Key Duties/ Responsibilities:**

- Managing and coordinating the production operations and staff to ensure daily production plan adhearance
- Overseeing the highest quality outputs of the Bio Products (dairy and non-Dairy factories)
- > Optimising the production operations focused to skewing down the production wastages & Costs
- Ensuring the most efficient machine utilizations and performance for improved OEE ratings
- > Formulating and defining work instructions and overseing their implementation for reproducable results and perforances within all the production sections
- > In liaison with the technical department, enusuring proper and timely machine maintenance and servising
- > Identifying the production staff training needs, planing and oveseeing the implementation of the trainings as well as evaluating their impact and effectiveness

#### **BIO FOOD PRODUCTS LIMITED**

From: May 2014 to Jan 2019:

**Position: Head of the Quality Assurance** 

Role:

- ➤ Reporting to the Operations, Quality, Research & delvelopment Manager; mandated to overseeing the systems for the production of quality products that meet the set standards and consumer satisfaction
- ➤ Heading and managing the Quality Assurance Team

# **Key Duties/ Responsibilities:**

- > To head and manage the quality Assurance team within different sections of work station i.e. Raw material reception, Sampling, Analysis, Products processing, finished goods stores and products distribution to the outlets
- ➤ Ensure compliance of all products processed (milk and milk products, jams and marmalades, honey and mayonnaises among others) with quality programs (GMP/HACCP) according to Bio standards.
- > Supervising timely milk outsourcing, milk reception, tiemly analysis, results delivery as well as ensuring compliance to hygiene and quality standards at all levels.
- ➤ Lead Bio sensory champions in daily products sensory evaluation to asceratin their conformance to quality standards before release to the market
- ➤ Proveide an oversight and guidance to root cause analysis and corrective actions with regard to any product non conformance both internally and externally from the suppliers
- Responsible for quality approvals of all Bio products before release sales for distributions
- Reviewing of the production processes and documents and recommend to the management for their implementation in tandem to the company's continuous improvement
- Advise milk transporters and all milk handlers on sensitivity and hygiene before, during and after loading and offloading of milk from milk delivery trucks and cans.
- Documentation of quality assurance and traceability records in all shifts of work for all the different types of products produced.
- ➤ Carry out training and awareness programs in hygiene, prerequisite programs (GMP) and HACCP to new employees and visitors on safety and quality assurance procedures as applicable.
- ➤ Involved in new product development, line process and product assurance in different sections of of products processes.
- ➤ Implement, monitor and maintained quality assurance systems guidelines and procedures for all the products produced.
- > Ensuring full compliance of all products with all government food safety regulations, and maintain highest level of food safety through daily monitoring programs, team supervision, and on-going verification by internal laboratory.

- Proactively identify potential and emerging challenges in processing, food safety issues and developing strategies to effectively investigate and advise Quality and Products Delvelopment Manager on quality improvements.
- Ensure quality specifications of raw materials and packaging materials are met by suppliers and their effective documentation according to Bio standards.

#### MERU CENTRAL DAIRY CO-OPERATIVE UNION LTD

From: November 2011 to April 2014 Position: Quality Assurance Officer:

#### Role:

- > Reporting to the Chief Executive Officer and overseeing all Quality aspects of the raw materials, intermediate and finished products as well as ensuring their compliance to the set standards
- > Overseeing the production systems for production of quality products
- ➤ Member of the milk procurement and factory operations sub-committee

#### **Key Duties/ Responsibilities:**

- ➤ Daily management of the quality assurance department.
- Monitoring of raw milk and milk products for compliance to the designed quality standards.
- ➤ Handling customer complaints and feedback on the existing products
- Establishment and/or adjustment of work procedures to meet testing schedules
- > Developing and recommending test procedures for raw materials and finished products
- > Designing HCCP plans and providing oversight on their implementation in line with other FSMs
- > Guiding on in-process checkups on process control parameters during milk and by-products processing and enforcing GMPs at reception, processing, packaging, and finished products sections
- Establishing and overseeing that proper controls and management of utilities at the reception and production/processing sections to levels that guarantees quality system for quality products
- Advising the other departments on maintaining quality standards on all milk products.

### May - June 2010 (2 months)

Kenya Bureau of Standards-Nairobi (Head office); Testing Services Department

# Position: Assistant Quality Assurance Analyst in Mycotoxins and vitamins, Food and agriculture and Microbiology labs

# **Responsibilities:**

- Conducted Samples Preparation prior to Analysis.
- ➤ Analyzed various samples for different quality control parameters.
- Carried out Sterilization of media and reagents.
- Performed reading of results, interpretation and reporting.
- ➤ Prepared stock solutions, Analytical chemicals and indicators.
- Organized and coordinated general housekeeping in the work place.
- > Operated equipments according to the standard operating analytical procedures.

# KEY COMPETENCIES AND SKILLS ACQUIRED

- Production planning, quality control and quality assurance management
- ➤ Internal quality auditor in Haccp/ISO 22000:2005
- ➤ Trained in Haccp/ISO 22000:2005 implementation by Egerton University
- ➤ Basic food handling and Hygiene
- ➤ Basic computer skills
- > Trained in community based first aid by Redcross and St. Johns Cadet

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2010 – 2011: Fortification of baby weaning millet flour using Vit -A from Cucurbita maxima and Iron from Amaranthus

Determination of the in-Vitro Bio availability of the iron

# **OTHER SKILLS & TRAININGS**

- ➤ Certificate in Occupational Health & Safety as per DOSH curriculum May 2021
- Modern Dairy Technology in India by Electser Company in Feb, 2013
- ➤ ISO 22000:2005, HACCP, GMPs by Prof. Abdul Faraj, Prof. Muliro & Dr. Muingei (Dpt. of Food Science & Technology, Egerton University)
- First Aid and Casualty management (St. Jonhs Ambulance cadet, Nakuru Division and Red cross Nairobi region)
- ➤ Computer Applications Level one (ICT Centre, Egerton University)
- Leadership training under Junior Achievement by Evans Ligeve (PriceWaterHouse Coopers)

# **SEMINARS/WORKSHOP:**

- **February 2011:** Participated in an interactive seminar Titled "A Wholistic life for young people" organized by Professional Accountants and Secretaries Association (PASA) – Egerton chapter
- ➤ Basic counseling skills & civic Education by Peace Unit Egerton University

# SELF-RELIANCE AND LEADERSHIPS

# President's Award Kenya-Egerton Njoro Unit

2009-2011: Chief Assessor & Awards Unit coordinator 2009 – 2009: Programme Leader and Activity coach

**2007-2009:** Award leader in charge of logistics and physical recreation

# Dairy & Food Science & Technology Association (DAFTEC)

2009-2010: Secretary

#### Makueni, Mbooni, Nzaui & Kibwezi Districts Egerton Student's Association (MESA)

**2009-2010:** Vice Chairman

2007- 2009: Organizing Secretary

#### EXTRA MURAL ACTIVITIES

- Member of the international award programme for young people; awarded the President's Award Gold Certificate (GAH) by H.E. the president of the Republic of Kenya, Hon. E. Mwai Kibaki in 2008.
- > Participated in a community service on Education Empowerment, HIV/AIDS awareness and campaign against FGM & Early marriages in Baringo district, Bartabwa division between 10th and 16<sup>th</sup> January, 2010
- Represented President's Award Egerton in inter-clubs soccer championship on 27<sup>th</sup> February, 2010
- > Participated in the National Expedition Challenge held at Mamba Village, Nairobi in Nov 28, 2009

#### **REFEREES**

Prof. Alfred Anakalo Shitandi, Ph.D Deputy Vice Chancellor (Research & academic affairs)

Kisii University College

Cell: 0722153494

Email: anakalos@gmail.com

Medical Bio Chemist; Food Safety and Nutrition Unit, Ministry of Health

Max Siteta Mutuku

Email: maxwexm@yahoo.com

Cell phone: 0722858783

Jacqueline Muthoni Food Safety Officer; NAS Airport services Ltd.

Email:

jacque.mso1@gmail.com/jacque

mso@yahoo.com Cell phone: 0724903500